Anton Shirikov

Ph.D. Candidate, University of Wisconsin–Madison 110 North Hall, 1050 Bascom Mall, Madison, WI, 53706

☑ shirikov@wisc.edu **۞** shirikov.com | *Updated:* Jan. 4, 2021

I am a political scientist working on media, propaganda, and the mechanisms of authoritarian rule. I also study legacies of authoritarianism and contemporary political institutions in post-communist countries. My research primarily relies on surveys and experimental methods.

EDUCATION

University of Wisconsin–Madison, Ph.D. Candidate in Political Science Expected Summer 2021

Dissertation: Who Trusts Untrustworthy Media? Partisanship and Information Credibility in Authoritarian Regimes

My dissertation project examines why authoritarian state-run media are popular and trusted, despite their strong pro-government bias. I use original experiments and surveys, conducted in Russia, as well as cross-national survey data to show that autocrats can rely on partisanship to prop up their media. Government loyalists find state-controlled media more trustworthy and more objective, and they rely on such media more in their news processing. My study demonstrates that partisanship is an important force that can improve the stability of autocratic regimes. I also examine how exposure to state propaganda affects one's ability to critically evaluate news information.

University of Wisconsin–Madison, M.A. in Political Science
Moscow State Institute of International Relations, Candidate of Sciences in Political Science
European University at St. Petersburg, M.A. in Political Science
2005

WORKING PAPERS

"Who Trusts State-Run Media? Source Cues, Bias, and Credibility in Autocracies"

"Is Trust in Media Decreasing? Evidence from the World Values Survey"

"A Model of Censorship and Propaganda" (with Scott Gehlbach and Dmitriy Vorobyev)

"The Oligarch Vanishes: Defensive Ownership, Property Rights, and Political Connections" (with John Earle, Scott Gehlbach and Solomiya Shpak) *Under Review*

"Smart Ways to Use a Postcommunist Dummy" (with Dmitrii Kofanov and Yoshiko M. Herrera)

"Legislatures and Executive Recruitment in Autocracies: Does Parliamentary Behavior Matter?"

PUBLICATIONS

2020. "Eurasia and Post-Communism: Weasel Words?" East European Politics and Societies & Cultures, Vol.34, No.2. With Yoshiko M. Herrera and Dmitrii Kofanov.

2018. "Sovereignty and Regionalism in Eurasia." In: Paasi, Anssi, John Harrison, and Martin Jones (eds.). *Elgar Handbook on the Geographies of Regions and Territories*. Edward Elgar Publishing. With Dmitrii Kofanov and Yoshiko M. Herrera.

2013. "Public Administration in Russia." In: Liebert, Saltanat, Stephen E. Condrey, and Dmitry Goncharov (eds.). *Public Administration in Post-Communist Countries: Former Soviet Union, Central and Eastern Europe, and Mongolia*. Routledge. With Dmitry Goncharov.

2010. Anatomiya Bezdeistviya. Politicheskiye Instituty i Konflikty v Budgetnom Processe Regionov Rossii [The Anatomy of Inaction. Political Institutions and Conflicts in the Budget Process of Russia's Regions] (in Russian). Saint-Petersburg: EUSP Press.

INVITED TALKS

Kyiv School of Economics 2020 Presentation: "Who Trusts State-Run Media? Source Cues, Bias, and Credibility in Autocracies" **CONFERENCES AND WORKSHOPS** ASEES Annual Convention (Virtual) 2020 Presentation: "Susceptibility to Fake News in Autocracies: Evidence from Russia" APSA Annual Meeting (Virtual) 2020 Presentation: "Who Trusts State-Run Media? Source Cues, Bias, and Credibility in Autocracies" Communication Crossroads (UW-Madison) 2020 Presentation: "Who Trusts State-Run Media?" Studying Russia and the Postcommunist World (Harriman Institute) 2019 Presentation: "Who Trusts State-Run Media? Evidence from Survey Experiments" ASEES Annual Convention (San Francisco) 2019 Presentation: "Who Trusts State-Run Media? Evidence from Survey Experiments" MPSA Annual Conference (Chicago) 2019 ASEES Annual Convention (Boston) 2018 Presentation: "Perceptions of Media Credibility in Non-Democracies: Evidence from Russia" Wisconsin Russia Project Young Scholars Conference Presentation: "When Do Russians Trust State-Run Media? Evidence From Survey Experiments" Regime Evolution, Institutional Change, and Social Transformation in Russia: Lessons for Political Science (Yale University) 2018 Presentation: "All the News That's Unfit: Exploring Censorship Choices in Autocracies" MPSA Annual Conference (Chicago) 2018 Presentation: "All the News That's Unfit: Exploring Censorship Choices in Autocracies" ASEES Annual Convention (Chicago) 2017 Presentation: "Returns from Autocratic Parliament: Post-Career Benefits for Russian Duma Legislators" The Annual Meeting of the Society for Political Methodology (UW–Madison) 2017

Anton Shirikov - CV

Poster presentation: "Media Bias in Autocracies: State-Controlled vs. Independent Press"

Workshop on Research Design for Causal Inference (Northwestern University)

2017

GRANTS AND AWARDS

ASEES Summer Dissertation Writing Grant (\$6,000)

2020

Summer Initiative Award from the Department of Political Science at UW–Madison 2020, 2019, 2017, 2016

Graduate student research award from the Center for Russia, East Europe, and Central Asia at UW–Madison (\$4,000)

Harriman Institute Research Grant (\$16,000; joint with Georgiy Syunyaev). Project title: **"Learning about Bias: An Experiment on News Consumption in Russia"** 2020

Harriman Institute Research Grant (\$10,245). Project title: "Perceptions of Media Credibility in Non-Democracies: Evidence from Russia"

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant for Kathryn Hendley (UW-Madison)

Spring 2021

Research Assistant for Nadav Shelef (UW-Madison)

Summer 2020

Research Assistant for Scott Gehlbach (UW-Madison)

2016-2018

TEACHING

University of Wisconsin-Madison

Teaching assistant for PS170: Research Methods in Political Science

2020, 2018

Instructor: Jessica Weeks

Math Camp for incoming graduate students in political science

2020, 2019

Lab and tutoring for PS919: Intro to Machine Learning

2020

Instructor: Adeline Lo

Teaching assistant for PS120: Politics Around the World

2019

Instructor: Nils Ringe

Teaching assistance for PS633: Russian Politics

2015

Instructor: Kathryn Hendley

SERVICE

Peer reviews of manuscripts for American Journal of Political Science, Post-Soviet Affairs, Problems of Post-Communism, East European Politics

Co-organizer of the **Comparative Politics Working Group** for graduate students (UW–Madison) 2019-present

Graduate student coordinator for the **Comparative Politics Colloquium** (UW–Madison) 2018-2019 Graduate student coordinator for the **Political Economy Colloquium** (UW–Madison) 2018-2019

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

American Political Science Association

Midwest Political Science Association

Association for Slavic, East European, and Eurasian Studies

SOFTWARE

R, Python, Stata, LaTeX, RMarkdown, HTML, Shiny, Git, Qualtrics

OTHER EXPERIENCE

I have previously worked as deputy editor-in-chief and editor-in-chief at Slon.ru, as opinions editor at RBC, and as editor at McKinsey & Company (all in Moscow, Russia).

REFERENCES

Yoshiko M. Herrera, Department of Political Science, University of Wisconsin–Madison, yherrera@wisc.edu

Scott Gehlbach, Department of Political Science and Harris School of Public Policy, University of Chicago, gehlbach@uchicago.edu

Rikhil R. Bhavnani, Department of Political Science, University of Wisconsin–Madison, bhavnani@wisc.edu